<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on After Math</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on After Math</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Robert Jacobson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 11:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Making a Pratt Parser Generator Part 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-08-13-designing-a-pratt-parser-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-08-13-designing-a-pratt-parser-generator/</guid>
      <description>A brief history of the Pratt parsing algorithm The history of programming language parsers is dominated by the thorny challenge of parsing expressions, mathematical expressions in particular, taking into account the precedence of operators in the expressions. Modern formal language theory began with the work of Noam Chomsky in the 1950s, in which Chomsky lays out a mathematical framework for linguistics. Under this mathematical framework, languages exist within a hierarchy of languages defined according to how difficult the language is to parse.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayes&#39; Theorem and the Deathly Hallows</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-07-01-bayes-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-07-01-bayes-theorem/</guid>
      <description>This article is an expanded version of the math part of an article I cowrote with marine biologist Dr. Andrew Rhyne about how many well-meaning public health professionals have misinterpreted the math behind test efficiency, Bayes’ Theorem. This misinterpretation has lead to dangerous public policy positions. Anyone with a math allergy is invited to read that article instead.&#xA;I and Dr. Andrew Rhyne, marine biologist and my longtime collaborator in fighting wildlife crime, have spent a lot of time in the last several months working on how best to fight the COVID-19 pandemic, especially in college communities like our own Roger Williams University.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining the Wolfram Language Part 2: Operator Properties</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-09-04-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-2-operator-properties/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 20:26:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-09-04-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-2-operator-properties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this third installment of our &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; part series, &amp;ldquo;Defining the Wolfram Language,&amp;rdquo; we begin to study the properties, namely the arity, affix, associativity, and precedence, of the Mathematica operators we found in &lt;a href=&#34;defining-the-wolfram-language-part-1-finding-operators&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;. If we ended Part 1 proud of our accomplishment—perhaps even a little smug—then we will get reacquainted with our humility in this article.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing PEMDAS: What is an operator?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-09-03-generalizing-pemdas-what-is-an-operator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 11:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-09-03-generalizing-pemdas-what-is-an-operator/</guid>
      <description>In programming languages, an operator is a symbol used to represent a specific operation such as subtraction of integers or dereferencing a pointer. The symbols +, *, and ! are commonly used as operators in many programming languages, for example. In this article we define some basic programming language terminology that allows us to categorize operators according to their different properties.&#xA;Computation with Expressions Virtually all programming languages have expressions, like 2 + 4, which consist of operators (the + operator in 2 + 4) and their operands (or arguments; the 2 and the 4), that is, the things operators operate on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining the Wolfram Language Part 1: Finding Operators</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-16-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-1-finding-operators/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2018 15:26:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-16-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-1-finding-operators/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;finding-all-wolfram-language-operators&#34;&gt;Finding All Wolfram Language Operators&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this second article, Part 1 of an &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; part series on &lt;em&gt;Defining the Wolfram Language&lt;/em&gt;, we start getting our hands dirty hunting down every single operator in Mathematica and each operator&amp;rsquo;s linguistic properties. To my knowledge, nobody outside of Wolfram has created such an exhaustive list before.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining the Wolfram Language Part 0: The Challenge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-07-02-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-0-the-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 20:14:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-07-02-defining-the-wolfram-language-part-0-the-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is the definition of the Wolfram Language?&lt;/em&gt; This is the first in a series of articles attempting to answer this question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The grammar of mathematical expressions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2015-01-28-the-grammar-of-mathematical-expressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2015 22:31:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2015-01-28-the-grammar-of-mathematical-expressions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using computers to do automatic translation has a long and rich history in computer science. A course in compiler construction is a veritable survey of topics in computer science running the gamut from formal languages to data structures and algorithms to Hopfcroft&amp;rsquo;s algorithm to minimize deterministic automata. One of the first things a student learns in a compiler construction course is how to formally describe the grammar of a language using (extended) Backus–Naur form (EBNF).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Mathematica From Python</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-12-10-using-mathematica-from-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 22:27:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-12-10-using-mathematica-from-python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In which I show you how to programmatically interface with a Mathematica kernel from Python.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Platonic Solids and the School of Athens</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-07-25-platonic-solids-and-the-school-of-athens/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2014 22:57:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-07-25-platonic-solids-and-the-school-of-athens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;euclid-in-the-school-of-athens&#34;&gt;Euclid in The School of Athens&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-UC44EGZXUfQ/U9LVe6BOFeI/AAAAAAAATQ4/Z3iy0xM4NVc/w723-h542-no/IMG_0537+2.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Me in front of The School of Athens&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a very special fresco painting by Italian Renaissance artist Raphael in the Vatican Museum called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_School_of_Athens&#34;&gt;The School of Athens&lt;/a&gt;. It depicts the great philosophers of ancient Greece, famously with Plato pointing up and Aristotle pointing down.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Springer sent me to collections for adopting their textbook.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-04-17-how-springer-sent-me-to-collections-for-adopting-their-textbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2014 20:52:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-04-17-how-springer-sent-me-to-collections-for-adopting-their-textbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story begins with one of those little mundane activities that fill every professor&amp;rsquo;s day. Right before the spring semester began I was evaluating various textbook options for the next time I teach undergraduate real analysis. Stephen Abbott&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Understanding Analysis&lt;/em&gt; published by Springer seemed to be exactly the kind of book I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Ask Your Professor For Something</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-04-12-how-to-ask-your-professor-for-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 16:33:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-04-12-how-to-ask-your-professor-for-something/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you need to ask your professor for an extension on a due date or to reschedule a quiz? A little thought before you click send on that email can make a big difference. Here is some advice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hangout On Air - Math: A Love Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-02-19-hangout-on-air-math-a-love-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 19:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-02-19-hangout-on-air-math-a-love-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/communities/100568607954673744130&#34;&gt;Mathematics Community on Google+&lt;/a&gt; had our second ever Hangout On Air last week. I was joined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+LuisGuzmanJr/posts&#34;&gt;Luis Guzman&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+JasonDavison/posts&#34;&gt;Jason Davison&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/+AmyRobinson/posts&#34;&gt;Amy Robinson&lt;/a&gt; in a conversation that ranged from fluid dynamics to applying the mathematics of networks to map our ideas to JPEG image compression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does a 1929 market chart predict a market crash?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-02-15-does-a-1929-market-chart-predict-a-market-crash/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 21:49:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-02-15-does-a-1929-market-chart-predict-a-market-crash/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No. No it does not. Not even a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sneaky Continuous Functions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-28-sneaky-continuous-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 21:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-28-sneaky-continuous-functions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script src=&#34;https://sagecell.sagemath.org/static/jquery.min.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;script src=&#34;https://sagecell.sagemath.org/static/embedded_sagecell.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;script&gt;&#xA;// Make any div with class &#39;sage&#39; a &#34;minimal&#34; Sage cell with &#34;Plot it!&#34; button.&#xA;sagecell.makeSagecell({inputLocation:  &#39;div.sage&#39;,&#xA;                       evalButtonText: &#39;Plot it!&#39;});&#xA;// Make *any* div with class &#39;compute&#39; a Sage cell.&#xA;sagecell.makeSagecell({inputLocation: &#39;div.compute&#39;,&#xA;                       evalButtonText: &#39;Evaluate&#39;});&#xA;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While the target audience of this article is my fantastic calculus students, other math teachers might enjoy it as well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sneaky-continuous-functions&#34;&gt;Sneaky Continuous Functions&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When students in first semester calculus first start learning about limits, they are often asked to determine limits using the graph of a function, which we will call the graphical method, and also by constructing a table of values of the function, which we will call the numerical method. Students should be warned that these methods, while perfectly legitimate and often quite useful, are really just fancy ways of &lt;em&gt;guessing&lt;/em&gt; the value of the limit, that is, the graphical and numerical methods do not supply us with mathematical certainty regarding the value of the limit. After all, what if your function is very sneaky and merely &lt;em&gt;looks like&lt;/em&gt; it&amp;rsquo;s approaching a value $L$ as $x$ approaches $c$ when in fact it ultimately approaches a different value $K$?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Susan Meisenhelder&#39;s &#39;MOOC Mania&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-28-susan-meisenhelders-mooc-mania/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 16:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-28-susan-meisenhelders-mooc-mania/</guid>
      <description>Susan Meisenhelder offers a scathing critique of MOOCs in her article &amp;ldquo;MOOC Mania&amp;rdquo; published in the latest issue of Thought &amp;amp; Action. (Here is a link to a ~5mb pdf of her article.)&#xA;The evidence so far suggests that MOOCs are great for a very specific kind of student looking for a very specific kind of product, but that MOOCs are really awful for some of the very groups that they are marketed to serve, namely students with less privilege (low-income, working class), and students on the lower end of the academic success scale (little education, poor performers).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blogging the JMM: Saying Goodbye</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-18-blogging-the-jmm-saying-goodbye/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 15:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-18-blogging-the-jmm-saying-goodbye/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s over. Getting my internet fix in the hotel lobby at midnight, walking 18 miles a day through the convention center, sitting in uncomfortable chairs for hours, getting dinner in a local restaurant and realizing halfway through the meal that every single person dining there is also a mathematician, randomly bumping into an old friend or mentor or student&amp;ndash;it ended today at around lunchtime when I made the trek back to the hotel lobby one last time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blogging the JMM: Friday</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-17-blogging-the-jmm-friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:41:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-17-blogging-the-jmm-friday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love the exhibit hall. I love books, and the exhibit hall is full of some of my favorite kinds of books. I spend hours picking through the texts, flipping through their pages. The AMS sold me on a great book directed at undergraduates on Fourier analysis and an advanced text on Riemannian manifolds. In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111299122922781685506/posts/jcXLNdoUcYc&#34;&gt;they managed to photograph me mid-purchase&lt;/a&gt;! I also learned they are selling &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111299122922781685506/posts/Apf42MJvpGx&#34;&gt;their first ever children&amp;rsquo;s book this spring&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blogging the JMM: Thursday</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-16-blogging-the-jmm-thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 17:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-16-blogging-the-jmm-thursday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The best part of the Joint Meetings is networking with like-minded people. I ran into many old friends and colleagues. Today (Thursday) several math bloggers and Google+&amp;lsquo;ers organized an impromptu meeting for lunch. I stuck a sign on the message board inviting other math bloggers to join us, and a cohort of tumblr bloggers discovered it and joined us. Such is the power of the JMM message board.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blogging The JMM: Wednesday</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-15-blogging-the-jmm-wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 20:53:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-15-blogging-the-jmm-wednesday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I learned about connections between musical rhythm and knot theory, abstract algebra and dance, a Navy ship from the mid 1800s called the U.S.S. Constellation, and some great undergraduate real analysis pedagogy. In today&amp;rsquo;s post, I&amp;rsquo;ll share with you some of the most interesting mathematical ideas I heard today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blogging the largest math conference in the world</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-14-blogging-the-largest-math-conference-in-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 17:05:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2014-01-14-blogging-the-largest-math-conference-in-the-world/</guid>
      <description>I am in Baltimore to attend the 2014 Joint Mathematics Meetings, the largest gathering of mathematicians in the world involving the American Mathematical Society, the Mathematics Association of America, and many other professional societies related to the mathematics profession. There will be over 2500 talks given on topics ranging from the mathematics of pop-up books (#489) to the density of Henig efficient points in locally convex topological vector spaces (#2341) to rational numbers and the common core (#903).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Students Die</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2013-12-18-when-students-die/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 21:05:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2013-12-18-when-students-die/</guid>
      <description>A colleague who had been worried about one of her star students who had been missing from class for a couple of weeks came into my office. “She committed suicide yesterday.” She needed to talk through it. She told me that she and two other professors had gone to the Student Services people a few days earlier—on a weekend—concerned about the student. She told me about all the ways they had tried to get to the bottom of what was going on in the days leading up to it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the IELR(1) Parsing Algorithm?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-10-10-what-is-the-ielr1-parsing-algorithm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-10-10-what-is-the-ielr1-parsing-algorithm/</guid>
      <description>This short article is for those students, programmers, and computer scientists who already have a basic idea of what a parser is and does but who want to know what that mysterious reference to &amp;ldquo;IELR(1)&amp;rdquo; means in the Bison parser generator manual.&#xA;The IELR(1) Parsing Algorithm The IELR(1) parsing algorithm was developed in 2008 by Joel E. Denny as part of his Ph.D. research under the supervision of Brian A. Malloy at Clemson University.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
